<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Infrastructure on Amar Prakash Pandey - ᕦ(ò_óˇ)ᕤ</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/infrastructure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Infrastructure on Amar Prakash Pandey - ᕦ(ò_óˇ)ᕤ</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/infrastructure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Docker - the right way</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/docker---the-right-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/docker---the-right-way/</guid>
      <description>Docker is a software framework for building, running, and managing containers on servers and the cloud. Here are the several best practices for using Docker in production to improve security, optimize image size and write cleaner and more maintainable Dockerfiles.&#xA;1. Use Official Docker Image as Base Image Always use the official or verified base image when writing the docker file. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you are developing a java application and want to build it and run it as a docker image.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GitOps - the easy way</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/gitops---the-easy-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/gitops---the-easy-way/</guid>
      <description>What is GitOps? Treat the infrastructure as code the same way as application code.&#xA;Separate repository for Infrastructure as code. DevOps pipeline. How does GitOps works? Infrastructure as Code hosted on Git repository.&#xA;Version controlled. Team collaboration. Use branching strategy to merge code in git repository. With CI pipeline to test the code. With CD pipeline to apply the changes to the Infrastructure. With the above steps we achieve: Automated Process.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finger Detection and Tracking using OpenCV and Python</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/finger-detection-and-tracking-using-opencv-and-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/finger-detection-and-tracking-using-opencv-and-python/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR. Code is here.&#xA;Finger detection is an important feature of many computer vision applications. In this application, A histogram based approach is used to separate out the hand from the background frame. Thresholding and Filtering techniques are used for background cancellation to obtain optimum results.&#xA;One of the challenges that I faced in detecting fingers is differentiating a hand from the background and identifying the tip of a finger.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
